<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>There is not any thing, which at this present concerns the kingdom of England, wherein its probable a ioynt consent and concurrence of King, Lords, and Commons will be had: as the wise and discreet managing of the affairs of Ireland, whether in prosecution of the war or peace.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95694</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867265</idno>
  <idno type="VID">169457</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240935555</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing T867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1190_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867265</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867265e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169457)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 167:E1190[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>There is not any thing, which at this present concerns the kingdom of England, wherein its probable a ioynt consent and concurrence of King, Lords, and Commons will be had: as the wise and discreet managing of the affairs of Ireland, whether in prosecution of the war or peace.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "London. 12th Decemb: 1644".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:169457:1"/>
            <p>THere is not any thing, which at this present concerns the Kingdom of England, wherein its probable a Ioynt consent and concurrence of King, Lords, and Commons will be had: as the wise and discreet managing of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Ireland, whether in prosecution of the War or Peace.</p>
            <p>There will not be much required to inforce this, every one can say that there is nothing more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy praise then to recover Ireland, without the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of England; but to do this requires great care and advice: for its well known Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was a Prince incomparable for wisdom, and had as good Counsellors as have been before or since is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome, yet do what She or they could, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting, and unfaithfull (if we may say so) mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of that war in Her time, had not only exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted the men, but the treasure of England in a great measure, King <hi>Iames,</hi> though wise in prosecution of that accord made by Her Majestie, yet unhappy in the instruments of latter Edition, and His present Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie first, and last.</p>
            <p>That this may challenge His Majesties present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence, and after full concurrence, take thus; he must not countenance at this time that Rebellion; because His Declarations, and Protestations to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are the only pillars that support Him in the hearts of His people of England: whom he in wisdom must now hold as faire with as he can, and at last smile upon, or it will be sad, let these troubles end when the<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will, and how they will: here after His Majestie must in policy drive on the same, upon the same ground,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169457:2"/>which consideration is a strong argument for the prosecution at present of any wise designe.</p>
            <p>This cannot cause any dissent from, or difference between the Lords and Commons; for they are joyntly not only obliged by their religious interest, but also in regard of such estates as they have, or may have here or there, for they may now from fresh and sad experience both there and here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that a long civill war reduces revenewes to a third, fourth, fifth, yea often to nothing; and that its a great impoverishing, to war for ones owne (which civill war is) though never so well managed, and expedited, and this may farther be said, that the strange managing of this present war both in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland, hath been the alone cause that it is not now at an end, and though its almost impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to lay a new foundation here, yet it may be done in Ireland.</p>
            <p>That which is desired and offered to the Lords and Commons in Parliament, and so consequently to His Majestie hereafter, is: That the most Religious or tender conscienced people in England, be intrusted and imployed in the affairs of Ireland for time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, This stands with as great policy as may be, for.</p>
            <p>First, they will be the least corrupted of any, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams in any thing is accompanied with most con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancie and fidelity: therefore are such usually the chief suffering men, they will not be made one while of this side, then of that, to favour now this, then that, to passe by this, take that, nor will they, nor dare they spin out for self good, that which is destructive to the publike: they look to the justnesse of the thing they undertake, and from that will not be drawn, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or any thing else.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they that have the greatest antipathie, or are at vastest difference in professions, are fittest to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169457:2"/>be imployed for the annihilation or reducing the contrary party, for we say, never fear deceipt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation between the fox and the lamb, between the hound and the hare, there is in nature to keep them at enmity, its ever so in the differences in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; we say sorrowing, a man lesse religious is easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie made this or that, corrupted, &amp; turned now hither, then thither: for this cause only the French State con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at the increase of the Protestant in Province <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedock,</hi> and other Frontire Provinces to <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Flanders:</hi> Vsually imploy such in the affairs of war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Roman</hi> party, and this was not the least that incited King <hi>James</hi> to call the Scots into <hi>Vlster,</hi> and with promise of Liberty of conscience, and also to give so much Land to the City of <hi>London,</hi> to take care of, because he believed that they would plant such there, though that thing they were more remisse in then in any other; and for this cause alone was Doctor <hi>Vsher,</hi> (that sometime eminent man for Religion as was pretended) made Primate of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> though there was a Serpent under that leaf, or came immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, these usually fight best, for this is clear, that men that live strictly, ever expect better hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and so are not afraid to change, because they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a reward in heaven; its true of an ignorant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist also, and of the Turks, and Nigers, in the way of their Religion: from the same principle, though upon false grounds: men of debauched lives beleeve there is a Heaven, and Hell, but are not perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the better, and fear the worse; they, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse carried on out of respect to earthly honour, are usually loath to venture their lives: this hath gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally been made good in these late warres.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they may be best spared, for we say such a man that is a strict Gentleman or Preacher, or the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169457:3"/>like, he will do well in the countrie, in <hi>Wales,</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> what doth <hi>Micaiah</hi> at <hi>Ierusalem?</hi> its not good he come neer the Court: King <hi>Iames</hi> sending strict men once to take account of the affairs of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving great content from them, he was advised to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them here, he said they will do well in <hi>Ireland,</hi> not so well in <hi>England,</hi> the neglect of this was the ruine of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had as many consciencious, as broken men gone, <hi>Ireland</hi> had at this day been all Protestants and the glory of Christendome.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they will best improve, for they are usually industrious, they think idlenesse is the mother of all evill, they dare not eat, unlesse they get: It was the consciencious people in the Netherlands, and France, that could no<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indure the Roman trumperies, who spread manufacture over England, and Germany, as is well known; this cannot but be great advantage to the State of England, for by this, they will be eased of great summes formerly sentihence for the defence of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which by industry will be able to defend it selfe, yea help to serve other sorrain or publike oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, and much increase the revenew of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, by this way that Kingdom will be secured from revolt or rebellion, either against the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> or by joyning with any forrain State: these by their maximes will not give way to the least thought of this, much lesse entertain any discourse that way, or act in that which is so directly contrary to Christs rule.</p>
            <p>Lastly, they who have adventured great summes for land in <hi>Ireland,</hi> will much sooner be possest of what they adventured for, and receive the fruit of, and that much quicker, and greater, and will have it better secured, and continued, which alone in reason should incite them to put up a request to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for those mentioned to be imployed; for when
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169457:3"/>they shall consider how things have been carried, what windings, and turnings have been, what revolts, and about, now to this, then to that, they cannot but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a ballancing power, that will carry the boat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes steady, that will keep the cart from being tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned over by every rub: is most necessary and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirable.</p>
            <p>But now the great businesse is: how to get these to go, for they must be made willing.</p>
            <p>First then, if these may be incouraged, by suffering them to enjoy their consciences as to discipline, and what more shalbe thought fit there (this being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted out of reason of State here in England) it may be a great invitement, and that its fit this be done, consider, they will not stay here, and if they go not thither, they will go where they will no way be usefu<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l to this State.</p>
            <p>Also there will be a great want of people, which before did abound: so that if Popery be extirpate, as thats sworn, there must needs be many thousands of Papists go also, and we know are already gone, and so there will be none to people places, and to till the Land, and give the Lord, or Gentleman rent, and this, if it were to the inviting all those now in <hi>Ameri<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> to return, were good reason of State; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, if these different opinions be winked at in the States Countries, a populous place, only out of this, that they bring grists to the mill, why not our own people, who by birth may challenge more, at least in that Kingdom where nothing is setled, nor suddenly can be in the way intended here.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if they may that are the souldiery part, be incouraged by entertainment in the present war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like expedition, by place of trust, and command set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled upon them, with such pay as the State at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent is able, and what cannot, at reasonable rates, in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169457:4"/>land to them, and theirs, in case they dye in the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or out live the war: it will be a strong invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them, which in reason should be condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto, and that because they apprehending, that their adventures here will not so immediatly conduce to their future content, by reason of that inevitable decree foreseen against them, but also by way of reward for unparaleld service, done by them in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall encounters, and if we should undertake to make it good, that its better to fall on in the war of <hi>Ireland</hi> more, though it were to the lessening of it here (things standing as at this instant they do, the adverse power being like now to be rather wearied in, then forc'd in) we beleive it might be done.</p>
            <p>But it will be objected, they cannot be spared here: Its answered, they may, and in reason of State ought, though this were not: for the other will necessarily, by reason of the conjunction, extort Presbitery in dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite of all, which is all desired, and if not, the antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie stretcht by the tongue and penne, is now grown so great, that it retards our publike service both in the armies, it being probable that the chiefe and secret reason of our not fighting the Kings army neer <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nington,</hi> arose from this, that that party might not have a second honour, and the fruits of it, a farther claim here, to a toleration; and also in the Assembly, and with all the divines of England Presbyterian, they looking upon them as those that will supplant them, or at least bring them into scorn with the people: which purports an inconsistencie clear, and presages not only great disturbances to the State: but an annihilation of one of the parties.</p>
            <p>Besides, the Laity are so enraged against them, that where ever they congregate, in City, or Country, they are lookd upon with such at evill eye distilled by the Clergy, that the people are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169457:4"/>far more forward to teare them in peeces then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, being found at Masse: this also appears by the Petitions that come out of severall Counties, praying the Covenant may be universally injoynd: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined to the bottom<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, is confessed to be for this end, to extirpate the independants, and not to bring in, or send out Malignants or Papists.</p>
            <p>A second objection, They cannot be permitted there because the Covenant is universally to be injoynd, its answered; that Covenant as it tends to the extirpation of Popery and Prelacy in such a way as the State shall think fittest, so it doth to the setling such a way in religion as shall be found most consonant with the word of God by them; and as a learned Doctor said, notwithstanding the Covenant, yet an Episcopacy may be erected, and why not a tolleration there of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependancy exprest, if the State thinks fit, these may have a kinde of toleration limited, restricted, and prescribed: but theres a third Objection; this will not please the Scots: its answered, it cannot be imagined that they having had what ever their consciences de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired, and was thought convenient to their State, that they should be against so good a publike work, so full of charity, and so directly tending to the good of the whole: but they expect say some, to have all <hi>Ireland</hi> as a reward for their service in <hi>England;</hi> sure who ever saith it, doth them exceeding great wrong: its clear they never opened their mouths in any so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable demaund, and why should we think they expect it? besides, there is in that Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> enough to serve them, should they leave <hi>Scotland</hi> emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; sufficient besides for all these before mentioned, and if any shall say, the harmony will not be good: its answered, there may be such order taken, that they may both serve themselves and these Kingdoms, of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> against the common enemy,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169457:5"/>without the least difference, and also enjoy each his conscience: besides, that cannot hurt in times of War, the occasions will be so many, and the assistances will be so equally needed, that they will not find rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to differ in circumstances, we know when they were at the siege of <hi>York,</hi> they agreed, never any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and in the fight at <hi>Marstonmoore,</hi> and yet it will be rare if ever such a neer conjunction be needed, as things may be carryed.</p>
            <p>And now a few arguments to perswade these peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to go, and to go to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, <hi>Ireland</hi> hath room enough, and the land is cheap enough; room enough its easie to prove: that there may dwell tenne times as many, as now are there, and live better then they ever lived in <hi>Ireland:</hi> land is cheap, it might be had for six pence, twelve pence, eighteen pence the acre when <hi>Ireland</hi> was in its greatest glory, and there are many houses unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molished, so that a man may possesse himself of as good an estate there for a hundred pound: as he can do in new <hi>England</hi> for a thousand pound, considering the length of the voyage: the charge of clearing, and building.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Ireland</hi> stands bravely for trade, neer to all parts of Christendom, especially <hi>Spaine, France,</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> hath good commodities for export, and may have far better: settle there once artists, and men of ingenuity, and it may equall most parts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendome: the contrary, as the remotenesse, and want of artists in New-<hi>England</hi> hath undone them, and had they arts, yet they want materialls, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, the voyage is so long, that ordinary commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties invite not, and if, yet the expence of the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age makes them not able to sell: but every one that hath the commoditie neerer, will under sell them, which was fully manifest, when passengers stopt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169457:5"/>trade ended there, and this may be said of any part of <hi>America</hi> that we can plant in.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the like sole content may there be had, nay better, for want is an impediment; give me not poverty: when in an handsome easie way of using the things of this life we may increase, its a most singular way to drive on the designes of Heaven, whether generall or perticular, want brings cares, cares eat out grace, as well as abundance: nay far more in a gracious soul.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God will have more Glory, in reason: for why may not a wise, a pious, and loving terrour, not only subdue those people, but convert them? It was the great argument that carried people to <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> the conversion of those people to beleeve in <hi>Iesue Christ:</hi> shew one man that ever was converted, or civilized to this day: the <hi>Irish</hi> acknowledge the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Heaven and Earth, <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> they are reasonable Creatures in the practice, may be wonne by teaching, and example; consider what by two or three godly Ministers was done in a few years in <hi>Wales,</hi> many hundreds brought home to <hi>Christ,</hi> and at this day shew forth the vertue of him that hath called them, above any its beleeved in the world yet now by reason of the War, wandring up and down in sheep skins, &amp; goats skins, a sufficient triall of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity in leaving large possessions, &amp; why should any think the <hi>Irish</hi> should not do the same? are they Popish? so were the <hi>Welsh,</hi> are they heathenish? so were the other: Theres no question but such cords of Love as these, holy examples, unblamable life, forgiving, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, instructing in the way of Heaven, with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, may bring in many thousands: its confest there is great reason that capitall offenders should be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, or rooted out, whether of one kind or other, which done, the people are wax, which it may be at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169457:6"/>first may be a little brittle, but after a little of the warmth of love mixt with the wisdom of the Serpent, you may impresse civility, industry, and if God please, grace.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, you will be able, better to support the truth, recover it, and suppresse who ever shall therefore op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose by force, your selves, or those that professe the same faith with you, which besides the reasonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the thing, the so much beleeved, and sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly expected destruction of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> may by this be much, yea very much helped forward, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, you will be a great impediment to any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain growing Innovations in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> nay it may be affirmed and made good, the Ballancing power in it, so as it will not dare to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, and if, kild in the shell, and this far better then by staying in <hi>England,</hi> and though there may be some risings against this, as to the other Kingdoms, by reason of apprehensions of unkindnesse, yet <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> hath laid that as one of his chief Commands, do good for evill, forgive your enemies, much more a brother when he goes astray.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the exceeding poverty of many of those that are this way inclined: we dare say many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands are destitute, more must of necessity every day grow, as trading decreases, and the warre prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: whereas there food and rayment may be got at present, that is, after once the souldiery is setled in the strengths possest; but if that should not, its but leaving the women and children behind for a while, which must be how ever, were not this set forward: little or no estates cannot go long voyages nor expect support by a common purse, which this may, and will have no doubt, because publikely imployed.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, there are many of these who have atchei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169457:6"/>places of honour in the war, which necessitates a deportment answerable, which calls for revenew after the wars are ended: which cannot be expected here, there it may, there are thousands of presidents in that Kingdom of such, whose merit in war brought them honour and estates.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, you will go neer to gain the love of the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. who though they are not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you should disturbe them here, which will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be, stay you: yet there you cannot; Brothers and Sisters agree best when they are asunder, some beauties are best at a distance, by constant intercourse in trade, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the amity will be strengthened.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, to perswade you; consider, you desire to propagate your way as most profitable and most au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick, why consider, there is a far better opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity there then any where, the 2. third, and fourth generations in wayes of Religion are usually declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions as to the heat: mettle taken out of the Masse works best, twice tempered makes it brittle: the brands taken out of the fire shine best, and heat best: those that think themselves best, are hardlyest made better, where sin abounded most there grace.</p>
            <p>But its objected, the warre of <hi>Ireland</hi> will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do all, and every foot of ground must be wonne and held by the sword first.</p>
            <p>To that, its thus answered, that warre well managed may prove a brave trade, and enrich: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the Netherlands.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this is not like to prove difficult, because there will be so many hands, as the Scots and British in <hi>Vlster,</hi> the supplanted <hi>Irish</hi> in other parts, who will be excellent helps, and great expediters of the busines, besides shipping will cut them short of all accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations from abroad: so that they may be starved into a subjection, there are that wise, pious, and of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169457:7"/>that with much confidence say, much may be done with a few men, and no great summes of mony: but if that stick, there is that to be said, that will take away this great objection clear, but not fit to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prest untill armies are there, and things composed here between the King, and Parliament.</p>
            <p>But it will be said, who would live by or amongst such a cruell and dangerous people? Its answered, that Kings have cares, its man-like to live in such a posture, as that he see his sword will come out of the sheath, whether his Musket and Pistols will off; to see to have his door shut when he goes to bed, to live in security, is effeminate, nay worse: Is it such a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to watch a little? the swine lies down and cares not how nor where; the only way to keep men in the right posture, is to have a condition mixt with a little war, their cruelty argues their cowardice, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sents them contemptible.</p>
            <p>The last objection is this, there will be a dividing of the party, its answered, theres the advantage, wheat sowne too thick grows not, the trees planted at greatest distance thrive best, be the ground good: its true, as to civill affaires, or rather martiall, some times the necrer, the better: but as to spirituall, the contrary; many that staid long together saw little fruit: but when they spread, the sound went through all the earth, of one may come many, yea as the sand for number.</p>
            <p>But what if the State shall think fit to permit them here? the designe notwithstanding may go as well on for the publique good: If we knew any thing of weight might farther be objected, it might be answer: if we thought the arguments were not strong enough, many more might be added.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>